Press Gang Publishers fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Press Gang Publishers fonds
[ca 1913] - 2002, predominant 1975 - 2000
F-184
Q106660837
8.29 m of textual records and other material
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
DATES OF CREATION Dates of accumulation are predominantly 1975-2000. Only one file (F-184-8-0-0-15) contains earlier material, some photographs relating to a book published by Press Gang. GENERAL NOTE Photographic material is located in series 4 (sub-series 2), 5, 7 and 8; see series descriptions for details.
Press Gang Publishers
Press Gang Publishers was a feminist printing press publishing quality trade paperback books—fiction, non-fiction, poetry and art—primarily by Canadian women authors and artists. Their non-fiction books addressed such social issues as the treatment of women by the mental health system, recovery from childhood sexual abuse, lesbian identity, homophobia and censorship, and women in conflict with the criminal justice system. Press Gang authors won numerous awards for their work.
Press Gang Publishers evolved from a feminist printing and publishing collective of the same name. The original Press Gang was a small collective of men and women who incorporated under British Columbia's Companies Act as Press Gang Publishers Ltd. in April 1970. By 1974, the collective had become a women-only, feminist and anti-capitalist printshop, with paid and volunteer workers.
Press Gang published its first book under its own imprint in 1976, a collection of essays entitled "Women Look at Psychiatry." Over the years, printing and publishing activities increasingly diverged, and in 1982 Press Gang established a separate collective to manage the publishing operations. In 1989 the separation was completed when the two collectives formally became distinct legal and corporate entities, Press Gang Printers Ltd. and Press Gang Publishers Feminist Cooperative. The two organizations, however, remained closely associated. In 1993 Press Gang Printers ceased to exist due to economic pressues in the printing trade and on their clientele (grassroots, community organizations).
Full-time staff members of Press Gang Publishers included managing editor Barbara Kuhne; financial manager Della McCreary; and art director/production manager Val Speidel. Paula Clancy and Nancy Pollak also served on the Press Gang Board.
Because of changes in the book publishing industry and the book selling marketplace, smaller publishers such as Press Gang faced difficult times. In 2000, Press Gang formed an alliance with Polestar Publishers of Victoria and issued a joint catalogue. Shortly thereafter, Polestar was purchased by Raincoast Books. In 2002, Press Gang Publishers declared bankruptcy after thirty years as a major independent feminist publisher. Some of their titles are still distributed by Raincoast Books and by Lazara Press.
published
Full
Revised
The title is based on the name of the creating body.
The fonds consists of records relating to the editorial, business and community activities of Press Gang Publishers. Activities and events documented include the evolution of Press Gang's organizational structure, and the separation of the printing and publishing operations; administration; collective, staff, Board of Directors and committee meetings; financial management, and grant applications; the management of royalties and rights; editorial work including manuscript receipt and evaluation; the physical production of Press Gang books; the promotion and marketing or Press Gang titles; and liaison with other feminist and publishing organizations.
Record types includes correspondence and reports; meeting agendas, minutes and supporting papers; photographs; grant applications and financial statements; contracts and agreements; manuscripts; book reviews and promotional material; photographs; and published books.
The material was arranged by the Archivist.
Kuhne, Barbara; McCreary, Della; Speidel, Val; Pollak, Nancy; Clancy, Paula; Photographic materials; Textual records; Arts and culture; Communications; Women
The records were donated to the Simon Fraser University Archives by the creators in 2004.
All accessions have been processed as of March 2006. Further accruals are expected.
For other material relating to Press Gang Publishers see the finding aid to Press Gang Printers, F-134.
Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as stipulated by Archives policy or the donor. Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
File and item lists are available.
- Organization and administration files, 1979 - 1999; F-184-1; 37 cm of textual records
  published
  Series consists of records relating to the administration and organization of Press Gang Publishers. Activities, events and topics documented include organizational history, governance and meetings, and daily office administration. Records include correspondence, reports, meeting agendas, minutes and supporting papers, and log books.
  The arrangement into sub-series was provided by the archivist.
  Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as stipulated by Archives policy or the donor. Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
  A file list is available.
  - Organization files - general, 1979 - 1999; F-184-1-1; 12 cm of textual records
    Sub-series consists of records relating to the organizational structure and history of Press Gang Publishers. Activities, events and topics documented include the separation of the Publishers from the Press Gang Printers collective in 1989, the evolution and restructuring of the organization, long-term planning, work agreements, the alliance with Polestar Book Publishers, Press Gang Publishers' twentieth anniversary, and the design of the company's website and letterhead.
    Records include correspondence, agreements, meeting minutes, catalogues, questionnaires, company profiles, reprints and articles about Press Gang, and notes and working papers.
    The first three files in the sub-series pertain to general organization history; the remaining files are arranged chronologically.
    - History, vol. 1, 1979 - 1998; F-184-1-1-0-1 (Archival box - standard 184-1)
      Textual records
      Open
    - History, vol. 2, 1979 - 1998; F-184-1-1-0-2 (Archival box - standard 184-1)
      Restricted in part
    - History, 1987 - 1999; F-184-1-1-0-3 (Archival box - standard 184-1)
    - Letterhead samples, [198-?] - [199-?]; F-184-1-1-0-4 (Archival box - standard 184-1)
    - Press Gang Printer / Publisher agreements, 1983 - 1990; F-184-1-1-0-5 (Archival box - standard 184-1)
    - Long-term planning, 1987; F-184-1-1-0-6
      Pending review
    - Articles on Press Gang Publishers, 1987 - 1995; F-184-1-1-0-7 (Archival box - standard 184-1)
    - Separation into two companies, 1988 - 1990; F-184-1-1-0-8 (Archival box - standard 184-1)
    - Restructuring, 1993 - 1996; F-184-1-1-0-9 (Archival box - standard 184-1)
    - Twentieth anniversary, vol. 1, 1995; F-184-1-1-0-10 (Archival box - standard 184-1)
    - Work agreements, 1996 - 1997; F-184-1-1-0-11 (Archival box - standard 184-1)
    - Press Gang / Polestar alliance, 1998 - 1999; F-184-1-1-0-12 (Archival box - standard 184-1)
    - Website, 1996 - 1999; F-184-1-1-0-13 (Archival box - standard 184-1)
    - Twentieth anniversary, vol. 2, 1995; F-184-1-1-0-14
  - Meeting agenda, minutes and supporting papers, 1984 - 1995; F-184-1-2; 12 cm of textual records
    Sub-series consists of records relating to Press Gang Publishers' meetings, including staff and collective meetings, committees, and the Board of Directors. Records include minute books, agendas, reports, notes and other working papers.
    Files are arranged chronologically.
    - Press Gang Publishers meetings, May 1984 - October 1985; F-184-1-2-0-1 (Archival box - standard 184-2)
    - Press Gang Publishers meetings, November 1985 - July 1986; F-184-1-2-0-2 (Archival box - standard 184-2)
      Restricted in whole
    - Press Gang Publishers meetings, August 1986 - June 1987; F-184-1-2-0-3 (Archival box - standard 184-2)
    - Press Gang Publishers meetings, vol. 1, 1987 - 1989; F-184-1-2-0-4 (Archival box - standard 184-2)
    - Press Gang Publishers meetings, vol. 2, 1987 - 1989; F-184-1-2-0-5 (Archival box - standard 184-2)
    - Press Gang Publishers meetings, vol. 3, 1987 - 1989; F-184-1-2-0-6 (Archival box - standard 184-2)
    - Press Gang Publishers meetings, 1990 - 1992; F-184-1-2-0-7 (Archival box - standard 184-2)
    - Press Gang Publishers meetings, 1992; F-184-1-2-0-8 (Archival box - standard 184-2)
    - Press Gang Publishers meetings, 1994 - 1995; F-184-1-2-0-9 (Archival box - standard 184-2)
    - Manuscript and business meetings, 1995; F-184-1-2-0-10 (Archival box - standard 184-2)
    - Board of Directors' meetings, 1995; F-184-1-2-0-11 (Archival box - standard 184-2)
  - Log books, 1989 - 1998; F-184-1-3; 13 cm of textual records
    Sub-series consists of records relating to the day-to-day transactions and administration of the Press Gang Publishers office. Records include registers and telephone message logbooks.
    - [Logbooks general], 1989 - 1990; F-184-1-3-0-1 (Archival box - standard 184-3)
    - Phone messages, 1993; F-184-1-3-0-2 (Archival box - standard 184-3)
    - Phone messages, vol. 1, 1994 - 1995; F-184-1-3-0-3 (Archival box - standard 184-3)
    - Phone messages, vol. 2, 1994 - 1995; F-184-1-3-0-4 (Archival box - standard 184-3)
    - Phone messages, 1996 - 1997; F-184-1-3-0-5 (Archival box - standard 184-3)
    - Phone messages, vol. 1, 1998; F-184-1-3-0-6 (Archival box - standard 184-3)
    - Phone messages, vol. 2, 1998; F-184-1-3-0-7 (Archival box - standard 184-3)
- Grants and financial records, 1984 - 2000; F-184-2; 51 cm of textual records
  Press Gang Publishers participated in federal and provincial funding that supported the publishing industry, including programs of the Canada Council for the Arts, the British Columbia Arts Council, the Book Publishing Industry Development Program, and the Association for the Export of Canadian Books.
  This series consists primarily of records relating to Press Gang Publishers' management of its grant applications and projects. It also includes some files relating to the organization's finances more generally. Records include correspondence; eligibility guidelines and other program-related material; and grant application forms, reports and supporting documentation (including title analysis reports, agreements, company profiles, operating data forms, financial statements, claims forms, receipts, invoices, financial statements, promotion schedules, and notes and working papers).
  Canada Council for the Arts; British Columbia Arts Council; Association for the Export of Canadian Books
  - Barbara Kuhne's file, 1984 - 1986; F-184-2-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 184-4)
  - Canada Council - Operating Data, 1984 - 1992; F-184-2-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 184-4)
  - Canada Council - Book Publishers Promotion Fund applications, 1985 - 1996; F-184-2-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 184-4)
  - Association of Book Publishers of Canada Computer Group application, 1987 - 1989; F-184-2-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 184-4)
  - Canada Council - Block Grant applications, 1991 - 1992; F-184-2-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 184-4)
  - British Columbia - Block Grant applications, 1991 - 1993; F-184-2-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 184-4)
  - Canada Council - Public Readings by Canadian Writers in Canada applications, 1992; F-184-2-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 184-4)
  - Publications Distribution Assistance Program applications, 1992 - 1995; F-184-2-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 184-4)
  - Canada Council - Block Grant applications, 1993 - 1994; F-184-2-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 184-4)
  - Assocation for the Export of Canadian Book applications, 1993 - 1994; F-184-2-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 184-5)
  - Book Publishing Industry Development Program applications, 1993 - 1994; F-184-2-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 184-5)
  - Promotions Program - correspondence and reports, 1993 - 1994; F-184-2-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 184-5)
  - British Columbia - Block Grant applications, 1993 - 1995; F-184-2-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 184-5)
  - Canada Council - correspondence and agreements, 1993 - 1996; F-184-2-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 184-5)
  - Multiculturalism grant applications, 1993 - 1996; F-184-2-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 184-5)
  - Book Publishing Industry Development Program applications, 1994 - 1996; F-184-2-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 184-5)
  - National Library of Canada - Large Print Program applications, 1995; F-184-2-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 184-5)
  - Quarterly financial statements, 1995; F-184-2-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 184-6)
  - Year-end financial statement, 1995; F-184-2-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 184-6)
  - Financial - general, 1995 - 1996; F-184-2-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 184-6)
  - Canada Council - Block Grant applications, 1995 - 1996; F-184-2-0-0-21 (Archival box - standard 184-6)
  - Grant applications, 1995 - 1996; F-184-2-0-0-22 (Archival box - standard 184-6)
  - Payment schedule reports, 1996; F-184-2-0-0-23 (Archival box - standard 184-6)
  - Assocation for the Export of Canadian Book applications, 1996 - 1997; F-184-2-0-0-24 (Archival box - standard 184-6)
  - Grant applications, 1996 - 1998; F-184-2-0-0-25 (Archival box - standard 184-6)
  - Provincial grant applications, 1996 - 1999; F-184-2-0-0-26 (Archival box - standard 184-7)
  - Grant applications, vol. 1, 1997; F-184-2-0-0-27 (Archival box - standard 184-7)
  - Grant applications, vol. 2, 1997; F-184-2-0-0-28 (Archival box - standard 184-7)
  - Canada Council - Block Grant applications, 1997 - 1998; F-184-2-0-0-29 (Archival box - standard 184-7)
  - Grant applications, 1998; F-184-2-0-0-30 (Archival box - standard 184-7)
  - Grant applications, 1998 - 1999; F-184-2-0-0-31 (Archival box - standard 184-7)
  - Grant applications, 1999 - 2000; F-184-2-0-0-32 (Archival box - standard 184-7)
- Contract, royalties and rights files, 1979 - 2002; F-184-3; 62 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to Press Gang Publishers' management of the legal rights pertaining to its publications, including royalties, distribution, use, publication and translation rights. Activities, events and topics documented include negotiations with authors and agents, distribution and subsidiary rights agreements with distributors and other publishers, and payment of royalties. Records include correspondence, agreements and contracts, permissions, sales reports and registers, and royalties statements.
  Files are arranged alphabetically.
  Some overlap exists between the content of this series and sub-series 4-2 ("Editorial correspondence") and 6-3 ("Author and book promotion files").
  - Anita D. McClelland Associates: Frankfurt rights, 1991 - 1992; F-184-3-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 184-8)
    Anita D. McClelland Associates; Textual records
  - Blackbridge, Persimmon: Prozac Highway - rights, 1998; F-184-3-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 184-8)
    Blackbridge, Persimmon; Textual records
  - Cameron, Anne: Daughters of Copper Woman - contracts, royalties, expenses, 1983 - 1987; F-184-3-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 184-8)
    Cameron, Anne; Textual records
  - Cameron, Anne: Daughters of Copper Woman - subsidiary rights, 1991 - 1996; F-184-3-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 184-8)
  - Cassell - rights, 1993 - 1996; F-184-3-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 184-8)
    Cassell Publishers; Textual records
  - Contracts and agreements, 1981 - 1984; F-184-3-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 184-8)
  - [Contracts - translation, reformatting], 1985 - 1986; F-184-3-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 184-8)
  - Correspondence - subsidiary rights, 1991 - 1994; F-184-3-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 184-8)
  - Dykewomon, Elana: Beyond the Pale - German rights, 1997; F-184-3-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 184-8)
    Dykewomon, Elana; Textual records
  - Fifth International Feminist Book Fair - rights, 1992; F-184-3-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 184-8)
  - General Distribution Services - contract, 1994; F-184-3-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 184-8)
    General Distribution Services; Textual records
  - Inland Book Company - contract, 1993; F-184-3-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 184-8)
    Inland Book Company; Textual records
  - Literary Press Group of Canada - membership agreement, 1996; F-184-3-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 184-8)
    Literary Press Group of Canada; Textual records
  - Mootoo, Shani: Cereus Blooms at Night, 1998; F-184-3-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 184-8)
    Mootoo, Shani; Textual records
  - Mootoo, Shani: Cereus Blooms at Night - rights, 1997 - 1999; F-184-3-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 184-8)
  - Open Letters Ltd: contracts, subsidiary rights, 1991 - 1993; F-184-3-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 184-9)
    Open Letters Ltd.; Textual records
  - Orlanda Frauenverlag GmbH: correspondence, 1996 - 1997; F-184-3-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 184-9)
    Orlanda Frauenverlag GmbH; Textual records
  - Permissions, 1991 - 1999; F-184-3-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 184-9)
  - Press Gang Printers - contracts, 1986; F-184-3-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 184-9)
  - Promotion - general, 1998 - 1999; F-184-3-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 184-9)
  - Rights - miscellaneous, 1997 - 1999; F-184-3-0-0-21 (Archival box - standard 184-9)
  - Royalties, 1981 - 1983; F-184-3-0-0-22 (Archival box - standard 184-9)
  - Royalties, 1984; F-184-3-0-0-23 (Archival box - standard 184-9)
  - Royalties, 1985; F-184-3-0-0-24 (Archival box - standard 184-9)
  - Royalties, 1986; F-184-3-0-0-25 (Archival box - standard 184-9)
  - Royalties, 1986 - 1994; F-184-3-0-0-26 (Archival box - standard 184-9)
  - Royalties, 1987; F-184-3-0-0-27 (Archival box - standard 184-9)
  - Royalties, 1988; F-184-3-0-0-28 (Archival box - standard 184-10)
  - Royalties, 1989; F-184-3-0-0-29 (Archival box - standard 184-10)
  - Royalties, 1990; F-184-3-0-0-30 (Archival box - standard 184-10)
  - Royalties, 1992; F-184-3-0-0-31 (Archival box - standard 184-10)
  - Royalty statements, vol. 1, 1993 - 1996; F-184-3-0-0-32 (Archival box - standard 184-10)
  - Royalty statements, vol. 2, 1993 - 1996; F-184-3-0-0-33 (Archival box - standard 184-10)
  - Royalties, 1994; F-184-3-0-0-34 (Archival box - standard 184-10)
  - Royalties, 1995; F-184-3-0-0-35 (Archival box - standard 184-11)
  - Royalties, vol. 1, 1996; F-184-3-0-0-36 (Archival box - standard 184-11)
  - Royalties, vol. 2, 1996; F-184-3-0-0-37 (Archival box - standard 184-11)
  - Sales and royalities, 1979 - 1993; F-184-3-0-0-38 (Archival box - standard 184-11)
  - Sales and royalities, 1988; F-184-3-0-0-39 (Archival box - standard 184-11)
  - Sales and royalities, 1991; F-184-3-0-0-40 (Archival box - standard 184-11)
  - Sales and royalities - register, 1991; F-184-3-0-0-41 (Archival box - standard 184-11)
  - Sales and royalities - final reports, 1992; F-184-3-0-0-42 (Archival box - standard 184-11)
  - Sales and royalities - register, 1992; F-184-3-0-0-43 (Archival box - standard 184-11)
  - Sales and royalities, 1993 - 1994; F-184-3-0-0-44 (Archival box - standard 184-12)
  - Sales and royalities, 1995; F-184-3-0-0-45 (Archival box - standard 184-12)
  - Subsidiary rights - correspondence, 1994 - 1996; F-184-3-0-0-46 (Archival box - standard 184-12)
  - The Women's Press: contracts, subsidiary rights, 1984 - 1997; F-184-3-0-0-47 (Archival box - standard 184-12)
    The Women's Press; Textual records
  - Warland, Betsy: Proper Deafinitions - US rights, 1990; F-184-3-0-0-48 (Archival box - standard 184-12)
    Warland, Betsy; Textual records
  - Witherspoon Associates Agency - correspondence, 1998; F-184-3-0-0-49 (Archival box - standard 184-12)
    Witherspoon Associates Agency; Textual records
  - Witherspoon Associates Agency - general, 1997 - 2002; F-184-3-0-0-50 (Archival box - standard 184-12)
  - Witherspoon Associates Agency: rights - payments received, 1998 - 1999; F-184-3-0-0-51 (Archival box - standard 184-12)
  - Women's Educational Press - contract, 1989 - 1990; F-184-3-0-0-52 (Archival box - standard 184-12)
    Canadian Women's Educational Press; Textual records
  - Womyn's Braille Press - subsidiary rights, 1990; F-184-3-0-0-53 (Archival box - standard 184-12)
    Womyn's Braille Press; Textual records
- Editorial files, 1976 - 2000; F-184-4; 1.5 m of textual records 5 photographs; General note: photographs located in sub-series 2, file 17.
  Series consists of records relating to Press Gang Publishers' editorial activities, including manuscript receipt and evaluation, and editorial preparation of manuscripts for publication. Records include correspondence, reports, manuscript drafts, and registers.
  The arrangement of this series into sub-series was provided by the archivist.
  - Manuscript registers, 1976 - 1996; F-184-4-1; 5 cm of textual records
    Press Gang Publishers registered all manuscripts it received for evaluation for publication. For each manuscript, the register records the date received, the author's name and address, the title and type of work, the Press Gang reader, and the response (rejected or solicited more material). The register was originally maintained manually in a logbook format. There appears to have been an Access database for a short time (1995-1996) as well. This sub-series consists of the three logbooks covering the period up to 1995 and a file of printed reports generated in 1996 from the database.
    For other material relating to manuscripts received for appraisal, see sub-series 4 "Submissions and solicitations."
    - Manuscript logbook, 1976 - 1987; F-184-4-1-0-1 (Archival box - standard 184-13)
    - Manuscript logbook, 1987 - 1994; F-184-4-1-0-2 (Archival box - standard 184-13)
    - Manuscript logbook, 1994 - 1995; F-184-4-1-0-3 (Archival box - standard 184-13)
    - Manuscript records from Access database, 1996; F-184-4-1-0-4 (Archival box - standard 184-13)
  - Editorial correspondence, 1980 - 2000; F-184-4-2; 70 cm of textual records 5 photographs
    Sub-series consists of correspondence files relating to the editing of manuscripts for publication. Activities documented include manuscript evaluation, editing, copy-editing, proofreading, copyright clearance, and development of promotional material such as cover quotes and book descriptions. Records include correspondence with authors and editors, drafts with revisions and annotations, reader's reports and notes, agreements and contracts, permission and release forms, author biographies and CVs, catalogue descriptions and other promotional copy, invoices, notes, and working papers.
    This sub-series is a group of case files organized by the author of the publication. The first three files relate to agreements and author correspondence in general; the remaining files are arranged alphabetically by last name of the author.
    Some overlap exists between the content of this sub-series and series 3 ("Contract, royalties and rights files") and sub-series 6-3 ("Author and book promotion files").
    - Agreements - miscellaneous, 1992 - 1996; F-184-4-2-0-1 (Archival box - standard 184-13)